Guide to the William Steen Gaud Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Steen Gaud papers
1925-1978
MS 941
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
Correspondence, diary, speeches, Yale memorabilia, and papers relating to his service as an administrator with the U.S. Agency for International Development (1961-1969) in the Near East and South Asia. The most important papers are his letters to his wife, speeches, diary and other papers documenting his military service in Asia, 1943-1945. Other letters to his wife describe trips to Japan in 1955 and 1956. Included also are two oral history interviews made for the Kennedy and Johnson presidential libraries, 1966 and 1971.
Gaud, William Steen, 1907-1977
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eleanor Smith Gaud in 1979.
Scope and Contents
The William S. Gaud Papers consist of correspondence, a diary, speeches, personal papers, photographs, printed matter, and memorabilia spanning his entire adult life. The most important papers are letters, speeches, a diary, and miscellaneous papers richly documenting his military service in Asia between 1943 and 1945. His service with the Agency for International Development is represented by photographs, clippings, speeches, memorabilia, and oral history interviews for the Kennedy and Johnson presidential libraries. There are also memorabilia from his years at Yale, letters to his wife from trips to Japan in 1955 and 1956, speeches from the 1970s, and letters of condolence to his widow.
The William S. Gaud Papers were given to Yale University Library by Eleanor Smith Gaud in 1979.
Biographical / Historical
(This vita was prepared shortly before Mr. Gaud's death in 1977.)
WILLIAM S. GAUD
1929 Received B.A. degree from Yale College.
1931 Received LL.B. degree cum laude from Yale Law School. Was editor of Yale Law Journal.
1931 - 1933 Instructor, Yale Law School.
1933 - 1935 Law practice with Van Vorst, Siegel & Smith, 25 Broad Street, New York City.
1935 - 1941 Assistant Corporation Counsel of the City of New York.
1941 - 1945 Army of the United States. Two years' service overseas in China-Burma-India Theater. Attained grade of Colonel. Awarded Legion of Merit with Oak Leaf Cluster, and Order of the British Empire.
1945 - 1946 Special Assistant to Secretary of War Patterson.
1946 - 1961 Law practice as a partner in Carter, Ledyard & Milburn, 2 Wall Street, New York City.
1961 - 1964 Assistant Administrator for the Near East and South Asia, Agency for International Development.
1964 -1966 Deputy Administrator, Agency for International Development.
1966 -1969 Administrator, Agency for International Development.
1969 Consultant, International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, Washington, D. C.
1969 - Aug. 1974 Executive Vice President, International Finance Corporation.
Oct. 1974 -1976 Consultant, World Bank Group
1976 - ? National Chairman, Population Crisis Committee, Washington, D. C.
Born August 9, 1907, New York, N.Y. Grew up in Charleston, S.C. In 1935 married the former Eleanor Mason Smith of New York City. They had one daughter, Anne Timothy Tinker, a graduate of Vassar College.
Prior to 1961 political and civic activities in Greenwich included: Member of Board of Estimate & Taxation; Member of Representative Town Meeting; Chairman of the Flood and Erosion Control Board; President of the Community Chest and Council; President of the Field Club.
Member of the Council on Foreign Relations; The Metropolitan Club; The American College of Trial Lawyers.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- East Asia; Asia; Diaries; Lawyers; Public officers; Soldiers; Gaud, Eleanor Smith; Gaud, William Steen, 1907-1977; United States. Agency for International Development; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1929; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1925-(1942-1978); 3 linear feet (3 boxes, 2 volumes)
  - Letters
    - William S. Gaud to Eleanor (Smith) Gaud, 1943 November 21-1945 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 1-19)
    - William S. Gaud to Mrs.W. Mason Smith, 1944 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - William S. Gaud to Eleanor (Smith) Gaud -- cables, 1945 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - William S. Gaud to Eleanor (Smith) Gaud -- transcripts, 1943 November 21-1944 April 16, 1945 May 3-7 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Letters from persons other than William S. Gaud, 1943-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - William S. Gaud to Eleanor (Smith) Gaud, 1955 September 13-18, 1956 October 16-26, 1959 August 15, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Condolences, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Military papers, 1942-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, 1944-1945, 1961-1962, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
  - Yale memorabilia, 1925-1931, 1941, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook of clippings and memorabilia, 1937-1943 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "Colonel W. S. Gaud, Jr., A. U. S., Personal Files": "Army papers", 1943-1953 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Speeches, 1943 May 6-September 28 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Diary, [1943] November 21-[1944] March 7 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Narrative of the trip to China (not completed), [post-1943] (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Photographs, [1943-1945] (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Passports, 1959-1973 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Photographs, 1961, 1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - A. I. D. personnel papers, 1961-1969 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - A. I. D. memorabilia, including letters patent, 1961-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Asian Development Bank, Inaugural Meeting: slides, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - The Business Council: guest lists and agenda, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Speeches, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Papers of Eleanor (Smith) Gaud, 1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Bank Group report, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - International Finance Corporation: miscellaneous papers, 1969, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Speeches, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 47-52)
  - Oral history interviews, 1966, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Financial papers re: ownership of a yacht, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Obituaries, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous papers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - "Scrapbook of William S. Gaud on Nomination as Administrator of A. I. D.": photographs, clippings, correspondence, pamphlet, 1966, 1968, undated (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook of U. S. government photographs, 1964-1968 (Box 5)